<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacobs great day of trouble, and deliuerance A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the fifth of August 1607. vpon his Maiesties deliuerance from the Earle Gowries treason and conspiracie. By Iohn Milvvarde Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Milward, John, 1556-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1028:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacobs great day of trouble, and deliuerance A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the fifth of August 1607. vpon his Maiesties deliuerance from the Earle Gowries treason and conspiracie. By Iohn Milvvarde Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Milward, John, 1556-1609.</author>
                  <author>Milward, Matthias, fl. 1603-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Eleazar Edgar, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Wind-mill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Matthias Milward.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Conspiracies --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JACOBS GREAT DAY OF TROVBLE, AND DELIVERANCE.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT Pauls Croſſe, the fifth of Auguſt 1607. vpon his MAIESTIES deliuerance from the Earle GOVVRIES Treaſon and CONSPIRACIE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>IOHN MILVVARDE</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for ELEAZAR EDGAR, and are to bee ſold at his Shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the Signe of the Wind-mill. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Noble, and Right Honourable, GEORGE, Earle of Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar, Lord <hi>Hume</hi> of Barwicke, Baron of Norham, <hi>Lord High Treaſurer of Scotland, one of the Lords</hi> Commiſſioners, equally conioyned for the middle Shires of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſometime called the Borders or Marches, Lord Gouernour and Captaine of his Maieſties Towne of Barwicke; and the Garriſon of the ſame, Knight of the moſt Noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt Honourable Priuie Councell in both Kingdomes.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He nature of true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is to communicate it ſelfe to others; it is a powerfull Agent, and would worke all like it ſelfe. It pleaſeth God to call great ones after his owne name, <hi>dixi dij oſtis;</hi> and good ones af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts name, <hi>Nolite tangere Chriſtos meos;</hi> to to this end ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, vt ſicut ſunt haeredes nominis, ſint etiam imitatores
<pb facs="tcp:13106:3"/>ſanctitatis,</hi> to ſhew how noble they are by deputation, and how worthy they ſhould be by imitation; that being the Delegats of ſo high a ſoueraigne, they might be <hi>dij tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares,</hi> not <hi>titulares</hi> onely. The mightie are ſaid to be Gods hilles, <hi>&amp; mons Domini, mons pinguis;</hi> though they firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue raine from heauen, yet they keepe it not to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but ſuffer it with ſpeede to ſlyde downe to the valleyes: they are the firſt to whom the Sunne ſhewes his riſing, and the laſt that behold his ſetting; yet being once mounted vp to his Meridian, the pooreſt Ant-hils then feele the vertue of his influence. Thoſe glorious lights of honour that ſhine in the faire Orbe of iuſtice, the Starre Chamber, they borrow their beames of brightneſſe from one Sunne; and thoſe beames they keep not to themſelues, but as <hi>Homer</hi> calles <hi>Apollo,</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>longe iaculantes,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting their ſplendor to inferiour bodies. For greatneſſe armed with goodneſſe is the ſanctuary of innocence, and whither ſhould miſery flye, if not to the mercifull? Vertue indeed hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and is to her ſelfe a ſufficient recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, <hi>ſat habet fautorum ſemper qui recte facit,</hi> nor needes ſhe like palliated hypocriſie proſtitute her beauty to popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity; for ſhe is the kings daughter, and her glory is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> amiable ſhe is, but not amorous, and with no other philtres then her owne worthines winnes the hearts of the Noble; yet like Truth that goes now and then with a ſcratcht face, ſhe hath neede of a Patrone, and lookes for protection from her true profeſſours; not to be magnified aboue her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, for ſhe cannot but to vindicate her honour from vile contempt. He that loues others vertues hath many of his owne; and it is impoſſible for goodneſſe to find fauour, but with the good. Amongſt whom (moſt honourable Lord) I find your noble ſelfe a Principall: and whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable loue to my deereſt brother if I ſhould forget, I were worthy, as <hi>Alexander</hi> once ſerued one, to be branded in the forehead with <hi>Ingratus hoſpes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>He that painted Ingratitude like a Fiend, meant her for hell, not mans heart; which like the Sea, for all the freſh riuers that fall into her vaſt boſome, is neuer the ſweeter; like a whirling gulfe, euer ſwallowing downe benefites, neuer returning the leaſt remembrance of thankes. The nine leapers that our Sauiour healed, had a worſe diſeaſe then leproſie ſticking on them, vn thankefulnes. <hi>Sapientis eſt</hi> (ſaid <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>bene debere beneficium, bene ſoluere, interdum autem ſolutio eſt ipſa confeſſio:</hi> ſo fals it out with mee (right Honourable) hauing obtained more then I durſt deſire, and wanting power to requite <hi>(nam tibi quod ſoluat non habet arca Iouis.)</hi> My heartieſt prayers muſt bee your beſt pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and no other requitall then a thankefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement. Accept therefore, I beſeech you, <hi>haac diuinae particulam aurae,</hi> this heauenly parcell, and bleſſed remnant of that faithfull and painefull Doctor, whoſe powerfull preaching, like <hi>Bonarges</hi> one of the ſonnes of Thunder (for he was a <hi>Iohn</hi>) many a Chriſtian eare hath with comfort heard; and whoſe worthy praiſe wil ſound better from any mans mouth then mine: He was my brother, therefore I forbear; yet me thinks to praiſe the dead and he deſeruing, were no flattery.</p>
            <p>That his life was fraught with croſſes, I impute not to any inauſpicious planet (though he found in his horoſcope ſome too malignant) but to Diuine prouidence, that with the frequent ſtrokes, <hi>malorum ſeu malleorum,</hi> he might be fitted for that heauenly Ieruſalem, where of he was liuing, a liuely, and dead is now an euerliuing ſtone. Yet this comfort God ſent him and his friends, to ſweeten the bitterneſſe of ſorrowes, he ſerued a moſt gratious Maſter, who loued him aliue, and honoured him dead, <hi>Cuius erat vinus, mortuus huius erat.</hi> For firſt his moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to whom he owed the duetie of a ſubiect, being his King, of a ſeruant, being his Maſter; did out of his Heroick and Princely clemency, a compaſſionate pitier of wrong'd ſimplicity, reſcue him from the jawes of conſpiring periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
<pb facs="tcp:13106:4"/>And after his death hath granted (by your Honourable meanes) an Annuity of an hundred pounds ſterling, for the better maintenance of his wife and children. And ſince it pleaſed his Highnes to hold him worthy of imployment into Scotland, I can teſtifie with what abundant ioy hee mentioned in his Letters, your Honourable name; how more like a father then a friend you reſpected him: and to vſe the words of his owne pen, which if hee had liued, the world ſhould not haue known, and which he wrote more for our comfort, then any vaine oſtentation: vnleſſe hee ſhould lie in your boſome, you could not vſe him more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly. Alſo that honourable Lord, the Lord Chancellor of Scotland, in whoſe houſe my brother departed this life; whoſe exceeding kindnes I ought neuer to forget: and if coſt or skill, paines or praiers could haue redeemed him from the graue, he had not died. Beſides the ſumptuous Funerall, the large remuneration of his ſeruants, all at your honours charge, do witnes to the world your Honorable diſpoſition, and how much you eſteemed him. Amongſt his other children (right Honourable) left behinde him, this which I here dedicate to your Honour, is one; not bredde of the mother, but borne of the fathers owne braine, like <hi>Pallas,</hi> for which he endured ſome throwes, and was by the helpe of a happy memory deliuered of it at <hi>Pauls</hi> croſſe. It is a poore Orphan, but rich enough if you giue it counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſafe enough, if protection. And the God of peace, whoſe Miniſter he was, whoſe Agent you are, and whoſe work this is, vouchſafe the light of his countenance to ſhine vpon you, and ſo encreaſe your earthly honour as you deſire the aduancement of his.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humbly deuoted, <hi>MATTHIAS MYLWARD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligious Reader; I am bold to call thee by a binding word, becauſe I ſuppoſe thee to be no looſe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. This Sermon is bound for thee, and may bee much bound to thee. Peruſe it, but miſuſe it not. Art thou a good Subiect? Thou wilt Reade it for the Kings ſake. Art thou a good Chriſtian? Thou wilt loue it for thy ſoules ſake. Art thou both? Thou wilt reuerence it for Gods ſake. Art thou neither? Why then for Gods ſake let it alone: The dead bite not, they must not bee bitten. The Authour is at reſt and gone, yet hee liues thou ſecſt. He hath vnboweld himſelfe like the Silke-worme, and died in a good cauſe, yet left ſuch taskes behinde him as may record his memorie, and propagate his fame to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie. The kind acceptance of this, may occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the comming foorth of more. If I haue done well in publiſhing it, thanke God for my ſake, if not, forgiue me for Gods ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in him, by whome, and in whom, and through whome are all things.</hi> Matthias Mylward.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:5"/>
            <head>MEMORIAE VIRI DOCTRINA CLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RISSIMID. <hi>MYLVARDI,</hi> ANGLI, S. SANCTAE THEOLOGIAE DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TORIS, REGIAE MAIESTATI A SACELLIS, &amp;c. IN SCOTIA DEFVNCTI CAL. <hi>AVG. I. D. C. IX.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIccine te ſummam nobis, Miluarde, ſalutem</l>
               <l>Dicere; nec patrios fas adijſſe Lares?</l>
               <l>Credo, tuam hanc duxti Patriam: viget Vnio: Doctor</l>
               <l>Quam viuens docuit, nunc quoque morte probat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>ALIVD.</head>
               <l>Quam bene, Miluarde, eſt? tua vox haec vltima nobis,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ecce citus venio: maxime Chriſte veni,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Venit, adeſt; frueris. Te ô ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quater<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beatum</l>
               <l>Laeta ferens alijs, qui rapis ante tibi.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Patricius ab Arenis Edinburgenus P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JACOBS</hi> GREAT DAY OF TROVBLE, AND <hi>DELIVERANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREM. 30.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Alas, for this day is great, none hath beene like it, it is the time of <hi>IACOBS</hi> trouble: yet ſhall he be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no Story more noble, nor of note for Fame better knowne, nor for Grace more honorable, then the Story of the Iewes and State of Iſrael, if
<pb facs="tcp:13106:6"/>ye conſider the vocation ſpeciall of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his familie, or the redemption of his poſteritie, from the yron and Aegiptian bondage, <hi>elutulentis manuum operibus,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine. Though the ſeruice was baſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 48.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.7.</note> 
               <hi>yet was the redeemer Noble,</hi> and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption <hi>copioſa nimis,</hi> as the good King ſaid; or if ye conſider the great benefites wherewith they were inriched, <hi>beneficia priuatiua &amp; poſitiua,</hi> as the ſchoolemen call them. Firſt, benefites conferred, or euills remooued; in one word to ſay as much as may be ſaid <hi>to ties liber, tot malis tot bonis toties auctus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12.</note> might make them caſt in their mind with that holy king and Prophet <hi>Quid retribuam? What ſhall J render to the Lord for all his benefites?</hi> So that when God giues, he doth not as many doe, which giue to Ruffians liberally, that which they ſpend looſely;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.40.</note> but as in <hi>Deuteronomie, vt bene ſit tibi, that it may goe well with thee,</hi> ten times repeated in that booke; for to that end God giues, that his gifts may be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: and, that you may ſee gods bounty too, he cals them <hi>omnia beneficia</hi> all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13106:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee with-holds nothing: Nothing that is good from them that leadea godly life: and then King Dauid cals them,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>84.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiadej,</hi> from the perſon to ſhew their excellencie, and to the perſons to ſhew their dignitie, that is, excellent gifts from an excellent giuer, giuen to men to make them excellent, that as the Hebrew word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken of troubles, ſignifies, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and quantity, many and great: ſo of benefits theirs were, <hi>multa &amp; magna,</hi> and all to make the threefold cord of duty ſtrong, whereby they might be bound to God.</p>
            <p>But with ill natures thus it happeneth, that fulneſſe is the mother of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and we alth and proſperitie Nurſes of wantonneſſe, in <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore complaines thus, <hi>Dilectus meus impin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guatus, dilatatus, incraſsatus, recalcitrauit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15.</note> 
               <hi>the people fed, fatled, inlarged, ſpurnedwith their heele,</hi> that is, were vnthankefull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and the Prophet <hi>Hoje.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oz.</hi> 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>They were filled, their heart was exalted and they haue forgotten mee;</hi> They forſooke their God, and iuſtly he caſt them off, and caſt
<pb facs="tcp:13106:7"/>them into the hands of Philiſtines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 4. <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.15.</note> Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Moabites, Ammonites. &amp;c. So that their ſinne became to them like <hi>Jonas</hi> to the Mariners, againſt whom windes and waues and all conſpired to caſt the fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ouer-boord; yet was hee neere and deare vnto God; whom heauenly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would not ſuffer to periſh, but hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his way with thornes, that he ſhould not runne away to his vtter ruine. And God thus tempered this peoples poſteritie with inuaſion of enemies, aſſault of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour euils, ſcorne of wicked men, with troubled ſtate, with bad gouernours, with continuall warres; and warres in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and miſgouernment, are like a three ſtringed whip for puniſhment, afterwards their kingdome was deuided, and at laſt they came to their worſt ſtate; captiuitie vnder the Chaldees for 70. yeeres together, who ouerturned the Temple, the glory of that kingdome, rooted out that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on almoſt vtterly, raſed downe their walls, burnt their Citie, and miſerably and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifully ſlew their people, bringing in
<pb facs="tcp:13106:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the lamentable times of famine, fire, and ſword, times ſaith <hi>Lactant. In quibus non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat iucundum viuere,</hi> euery where being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with trembling and horrour; their daies now likened by this Prophet in this Chapter to the dayes of Child-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, wherin their men like women in trauell, put their hands vpon their loynes and all their faces were turned into pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which made the Prophet cry out, <hi>Vae, quia, &amp;c. Alas, for this day is great, none hath beene like it, it is the time of Iacobs trouble, yet ſhall he be deliuered from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words are two generall points contayned, viz. Firſt the Sorrowfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of Iacob. Secondly the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which followed.</p>
            <p>In the firſt I obſerue foure things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A vehement exclamation, a very <hi>Vae, Alas,</hi> more then a ſadde and heauie groane; ſorrow of a deepe impreſsion, from the very hearts roote, ſighing, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <p>Secondly, A confirmation of it with a reaſon, to ſhew he cries not without cauſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13106:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Alas, for this day is great,</hi> in which, are two words, <hi>dies,</hi> &amp; <hi>magnus,</hi> there is <hi>breuitas</hi> and <hi>grauitas,</hi> not ſhort and ſweet, but like to anger, <hi>ſi breuis grauis. viz.</hi> If it bee ſhort, it is ſharpe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A reaſon vpon reaſon, it is a <hi>great day,</hi> why ſo? for <hi>none hath beene like it,</hi> and this is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> very forcible, ſuch a day as neuer was the like; a ſtrong &amp; a ſtrange amplification of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>The fourth part ſpeakes out; for in the other three, ſorrow ſpake in her owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that is, ſcarce could ſpeake at all, but chatter like a Crane or like a Swallow, as <hi>Hezechias</hi> did; this fourth declares all: Where the firſt is an exclamation, theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond a confirmation, the third an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration none like it; the fourth is an expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and telles what all this ſorrow meanes, <hi>It is the time of Iacobs trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond part is ſacobs conſolation, and in it are three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the promiſe he ſhalbe deliuered, a word of a future time, not he hath been, not now, no nor yet; but he ſhall be, and
<pb facs="tcp:13106:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>this noteth three other matters.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Iacob muſt haue patience and tarry Gods leyſure.</item>
               <item>2 That he muſt hope then moſt, where reaſon is leaſt;</item>
               <item>3 He muſt not be weake-handed, nor faint-harted, leaſt he droupe ere the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe be fulfilled.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, heere is an vnion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with their head <hi>Iacob,</hi> and all <hi>Iacob; rex &amp; populus, Iacob</hi> and euery <hi>Iacob,</hi> that is, euery holy man ſhall ſuffer tribulation, but he ſhall ouercome it, and riſe like Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el out of the Sea.</p>
            <p>The third is in the words <hi>Sed tamen,</hi> which implies a mighty defence of God on <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſide, as if he ſhould ſay although they ſhould conſpire by fraud or force to put <hi>Iacob</hi> downe, and as the prouerb is <hi>pes pede denſuſqueviro vir,</hi> band themſelues, and hand in hand with weapons in their hand, endeuour to take <hi>Iacobs</hi> life away; yet let him beare his trouble, it is but for a time, <hi>Sed tamen,</hi> that is, <hi>I the God of Iacob, in ſpight of them all, I will deliuer him:</hi> and this
<pb facs="tcp:13106:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the ſumme of this verſe, and as I take it the fitteſt text that could bee choſen for the time.</p>
            <p>This verſe begins like the life of man, with a mournfull ditty, Alas, a note of ſorrow, and,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Puer qui naſcitur a ploratu incipit</hi> begins with crying; <hi>neſciens prophetizat quid malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum paſſurus ſit,</hi> and is at firſt a prophet of his owne aduerſityes; and all experience tels vs it is true, and neuer any heard of but <hi>Zoroaſtes,</hi> the great Magician, who is ſaid to haue laughed when he was borne. Theſe words are <hi>Speculum humanae vitae</hi> the very glaſſe of life, repreſenting to all men alike their common lot in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall forheades and beginnings. So that if we conſider nature only, it is true that one obſerued, mans life for his entrance is blindneſſe, his birth a crying, his progreſſe labour, and his end dolour, euery where error: and now a ſorrowfull Alas ſalutes me at the threſhold, like a churliſh porter to ſhut the doore where ioy would enter; ſo that me thinks, I doe not ſpeake but groane, and rather weepe then perſwade.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Poets faine that <hi>Iupiter</hi> hath two great tunnes or veſſels, of which euery man at his birth muſt take his draught; the one is proſperity; the other is aduerſity; of the firſt he may but ſip, of the laſt he ſhall haue ſtore Yf you marke the ouerthwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; of life and the croſſes of all mens ſtates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid true <hi>Lacrimae potius deerunt quam cauſae dolendi,</hi> yea Saints and holy men when they doe plead with God as <hi>Iob</hi> cals it, cannot, nor dare not fill their mouthes with arguments, but lay their hand vpon their mouthes and ſo make ſupplication to their iudge, <hi>plus gemitibus quam ſer moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> with ſighes, rather then ſayings, ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome;</hi> and treat with him, <hi>affectu po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam affatu,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Firſt with remorce rather then diſcourſe. The holieſt King in his 88. <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.15. Thren. 3.</note> 
               <hi>from my youth vp thy terrors haue I ſuffered</hi> and he ſaid not <hi>dolores,</hi> but <hi>terrores,</hi> well, that was in youth; and it is good (ſaith <hi>Jeremie</hi>) <hi>for a man to beare the yoake in his youth;</hi> but ſhould not his age be better comforted? no. But as <hi>Martyr</hi> ſaith, though God forgaue his
<pb facs="tcp:13106:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinne and gaue him fauour, yet he ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as if God had reſerued him <hi>ad vitam plenam crucibus. viz.</hi> To liue and die an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted man. The wiſeſt King in his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching booke againſt vanity, hath this graue ſentence;<note place="margin">Eccle. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it is better to goe to the houſe of mourning then of feaſting:</hi> wiſe men are mourners for the moſt part, and it is better to goe from teares to ioy 'then from your ioy to weeping; labour and ſorrowe are the twinnes of ſinne, borne at a birth, and our life is an <hi>Hermaphrodite</hi> conſiſting of both ſexes, pertaking of both. For to <hi>Adam</hi> God ſaid, <hi>in ſudore uultus tui;</hi> and addes, <hi>manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis in labore;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. &amp; 3.16.</note> there is ſweat and toyle and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for the man: and to the woman he ſaid, <hi>paries in labore,</hi> and there is ſorrowe for the woman; ſorrow is her portion; one of theſe for them both, if not both theſe for either one. But if you come to Prophets and there happen to find <hi>Daniell</hi> to be <hi>vir deſideriorum,</hi> as the old tranſlator reades, you ſhall find that <hi>Ieremie</hi> is <hi>vir dolorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Ior.</hi> 10.19.</note> a man of ſorrowe, and crying out <hi>vae mihi propter rupturam; Alas</hi> and woe is me for
<pb facs="tcp:13106:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>my breach, <hi>plag mea dolorifica,</hi> my plague is ſorrowfull; the old tranſlator ſaith, it is <hi>plaga peſſima,</hi> a ſuperlatiue plague; but yet <hi>Ieremie</hi> is couragious, and ſtruggles not impatiently, but reſoluedly layer hit to his ſhoulder ſaying, this is <hi>dolor meus,</hi> my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and I will beare it. And without doubt this <hi>Alas</hi> is great, for the day is great, and none hath bene like it, and a day and a ſorrowe that made a ſorrowfull day, and a day of ſuch a ſorrowe as made him ſay <hi>non fuit ſimilis illi,</hi> and, <hi>non eſtdolor ſicut dolor meus;</hi> that firſt is in my text,<note place="margin">Thren. 1.12.</note> and this other fitly placed in the Lamentations, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken alſo properly of <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> miſery, and by the auncient fathers referred vnto Chriſt. Let this <hi>Alas</hi> ſtand for a great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe; yet whether ſorrowe will or no, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe hath this comfort in it, <hi>nemo poteſt valde dolere at que diu,</hi> no man can ſorrowe much and ſorrowe long; for nature (ſaith the Philoſopher) we ſay (God) hath made euery ſorrowe, <hi>ſi non breuem, at certe tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem,</hi> that is, either a man ſhall quickly weare it out, or beare it out.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Let therefore no man wonder, for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie things are mixed with ioyfull, <hi>in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinam</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for phiſicke to the ſoule; and Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate &amp; ſeueritate</hi> God doth temper <hi>ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare poculum</hi> the health-bringing cup. For as before is ſaid, the wiſeſt men are mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo euery good man is <hi>vir lachrimabilis</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, good men are wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping men and compoſe <hi>mentem ad lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> they order their minds to mourning vpon the worlds ruthfull accidents. And it is true that <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid, <hi>ni ratio finem fecerit fortuna non faciet.</hi> Well, if ſound eyes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not looke on ſore eyes, but will ſhedde teares, and be like affected; what heart can ioy in ſuch a day, ſuch a time, in ſuch a word of ſorrow? Barbarians haue iudged it ſhamefull and a fault not then to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, when if not all, yet beſt men ſorrow, <hi>Alas,</hi> to ſing ſongs to a heauie heart, is <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>-like, that plaide on his harpe while the Citie was burning: the Greeke Orator ſaid well <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wha is out of ſeaſon is out of reaſon: if an Ah, of a
<pb facs="tcp:13106:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſigh or a groane, bends and rends the hart with ſuch a <hi>tangit &amp; angit,</hi> what thinke you of this Oh? this <hi>Alas,</hi> this <hi>Vae,</hi> the note for the moſt part (ſaith Chriſoſtom) of damnation eternall; it is at leaſt a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſorrow that turnes <hi>lumina</hi> in <hi>flumina,</hi> in <hi>fontem frontem,</hi> eyes into teares, and face into a fountaine:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.1.</note> yea that turnes all faces in <hi>auruginem</hi> paleneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.6.</note> as in the verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Yea into blacknes blacker then blacknes, Lamentations,</hi> 4.8. and <hi>Pagnine</hi> and <hi>Vata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blus</hi> ſo tranſlate it. Sad and mournefull lookes declare a heauie heart, ſuch is the face of my text, where in the forehead this Alas is fixed as the ſigne of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>So would the Creator that his creature ſhould make his progreſſe like the noble Patriarchs; I am no better then my fathers,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.4.</note> ſaith good, yet ſorrowfull <hi>Eliah:</hi> Oh that we were ſo good! but looke vpon their ſorrowes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> and you ſhall ſee <hi>Adams</hi> heart melting for the parricides curſe, and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for <hi>Abel,</hi> whoſe name ſignifies mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; me thinkes I ſee <hi>Noah</hi> grieuing to pronounce a curſe vpon his owne ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:13106:12"/>and to ſee <hi>Chams</hi> Chanaan accurſed from the father to the ſonne in their poſterities.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25.</note> Looke vpon <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> Gods friends, wandring vp and downe like pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes, and ſetled no where ſaue in God onely: and <hi>Iacob</hi> that is, <hi>fons omnium diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinarum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calles him, what ſorrowes did he ſuffer, which made him confeſſe his daies few and euill? Looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Iſraelites purſued with <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hoſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 47.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.28</note> to paſſe the ſea of blood, by the deſart and fierie Serpents to winne the promiſed land. Goe a little further, and ſee the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſee how Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaks of them together, <hi>An putatis fratres, quod Prophetae iocando prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicent, ridendo loquantur apoſtoli, aut Christus infantiliter comminetur; ſed ioci non ſunt vbi tormenta intercedunt: Eſaias ſerra ſecatur, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel leonibus deuorandus exponitur; Petrus in cruce, Dei exemplo ſuſpenditur. Si iocando ſunt paſsi, credo &amp; iocando ſuut loquuti.</hi> But wee may feare the worlds faith, to be rather a ſporting faith then theirs was: they went the way to the Kingdome, as beautifull
<pb facs="tcp:13106:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Naomi</hi> did by <hi>Marah,</hi> that is bitterneſſe. The beginning of the Prince of ſaluation was with a <hi>Vae,</hi> Alas, heauie and ſad en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; borne poore, and yet perſecuted; driuen to flie, and into Aegypt; yet ſaith <hi>Chryſostome, perſecutor primogeniti fit cuſtos vnigeniti,</hi> let his life goe, for it went for vs: what did he? <hi>Tertullian</hi> telles vs the order, that <hi>Chriſtus fauos poſt fella guſtauit,</hi> after the gall of the Croſſe, hee was to taſt honny combes of glory, and was not ſaluted of the heauenly company, <hi>ante quam rex Iudeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum proſcriptus in cruce;</hi> and there beginnes his Trophee.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.7.9.</note> What meanes theſe wounds in thy hands, ſaith the Prophet? And the anſwere is, <hi>ſic percuſſus ſum ab amicis:</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> like an Herald went before, proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Lift vp your heads ye gates, and be ye lift vp ye euerlaſting doores, and let the King of Glorie come in. The Cherubims &amp; Seraphims, the heauenly hoaſt, &amp; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe called, to ſee and heare ſuch a call were amazed, and aske, <hi>Quis eſt iſte rex gloriae?</hi> Who is this king of glorie? at laſt they knew him, it is the Lord of Hoaſts,
<pb facs="tcp:13106:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp;c. He that firſt paſſed from Edom with his garments ſo red as in blood; that went by Acheldama,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note> and by the croſſe: ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, Et tu perge; non eſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iter ad cellaria regis niſi per torcular crucis:</hi> therfore if you wil <hi>Chriſtum ſe qui &amp; conſequi,</hi> follow Chriſt and come to Chriſt, ſhrug not, nor ſhrinke not, nor ſhift not the Croſſe, nor thinke to make it laſt: this Alas wil ſtand no where ſo well as in the beginning, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelues this Alas will ſalute you firſt: and that for three reaſons,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to weane vs from the world, as Nurſes doe their children, annointing their breaſts with ſome bitter thing: ſo dooth almightie God, to make vs loath and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the worlds ſweetneſſe, ſeaſons thy life with ſorrowes more bitter then gall, and yet all muſt be borne, ſo the end may be ſweete: is not ſhort paine well borne, that brings long eaſe? peace is moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come after wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and hauen after ſtormy ſeas: aftera ſad life glad death, and after combat conqueſt, <hi>aut citò mors venit aut vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria laeta,</hi> ſaid the Poet.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, that euery mans mind might by dayly exerciſes in bearing aduerſities be made more manly. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith <hi>Animus ſtabiliendus eſt constantia, vt nullis frangatur moleſtiis, &amp;c.</hi> a good man will not bee daunted with any ſtormes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though like <hi>Samſon</hi> he encounter Giants, or like <hi>Dauid</hi> wreſtles and fights with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Beares, becauſe he knowes how God firſt makes fit, and after brings him to the fight.</p>
            <p>Thirdly that we might conſider Gods iudgements and their cauſes, what they are, and on whom they faſten, learning thereby to waite for the Lord in <hi>vijs iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum,</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, who will then turne your <hi>Vae</hi> into an <hi>Aue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 26.8.</note> your meate of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, as <hi>Job</hi> calls it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 6.7.</note> into the feaſt of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, your lamentings into reioicings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.4.</note> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the face of ſorrowes, and wyping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all teares from your eyes? Therefore the Prophet here to inferre the greatneſſe of the griefe, in the very entrance placed the name and note of ſorrowe, ſhewing hearty and in-bred ſorrow; not in <hi>labris,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:14"/>but in <hi>fibris:</hi> a <hi>Vae,</hi> that is, Alas, not ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but with a deepe and a heauie grone, a ſtrong and ſharpe exclamation, confirmed with a reaſon; that you ſhould not thinke he did as wantons doe, crie and haue no cauſe, but hee cries out, and brings good reaſon for it: <hi>Alas, For this day is great, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There haue many great daies beene in former times,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.</note> and amongſt them all that <hi>dies vnus,</hi> which was <hi>dies primus,</hi> the firſt day, when God called the light day, and that was <hi>dies dierum;</hi> the day before which there was no day, which verily was <hi>dies magnus.</hi> Yet that ſame addition giuen to the ſeuenth day, that it ſhould be ſanctified <hi>dies ſanctus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.4.</note> a holy day, the reſt of good and holy ſoules, the bleſſed and ſanctified day; that day is <hi>dies magnus.</hi> And of theſe <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes with admiration, <hi>in die, qua Deus creauit caelum!</hi> and againe, <hi>in die, qua creauit Deus hominem!</hi> in that day too wherein God created man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.1.</note> What would <hi>Moyſes</hi> haue ſaid of the day of the worlds redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he had liued to it? certainely a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a farre better day, <hi>nam plus mihi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit
<pb facs="tcp:13106:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Deus redimendo, quam creando,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe; quia creando me mihi dedit; redimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ſeipſum pro me, &amp; me mihi reddidit: ſi totum de beo pro me facto, quid iam reddam pro me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto?</hi> Both the daies were glorious daies, the creation and redemption: but yet here the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeakes of another day, that is, of the diſtreſſe and affliction of this people in the name of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſo it was <hi>dies magnus.</hi> Two words implying two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Breuity, for that it is but a day, vſed to expreſſe ſmall continuance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Grauity, and weight of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in that word <hi>magnus,</hi> which implyeth ſharpenes and the extent of affliction.</p>
            <p>Short it is, but for a day, and <hi>dies vnus:</hi> ſo when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſummes vp <hi>Methuſhelah</hi> his life, he then numbers (as in <hi>Iob, vita vnius diei</hi>) his life by a day, and ſets one day for his life; but when he gathers particulars to make the totall, then he ſaith, All the daies of <hi>Methuſhelah,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.</note> And <hi>Iacob</hi> to <hi>Pharoah</hi> makes mention in one verſe once of yeares, and thrice of da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es: if this life be
<pb facs="tcp:13106:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhort by yeares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.</note> it is ſhorter by daies; though <hi>Abraham,</hi> as the Text ſaith, liued full of daies, yet he and others gaue place to nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34.</note> and were not more full <hi>dierum</hi> then <hi>dolorum.</hi> The truth hath ſpoken it, <hi>ſufficit diei malitia: i.</hi> the ſorrow or vexation of it: <hi>Moſes</hi> couples labour and dolour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.10.</note> &amp; ſuch a day was <hi>Iacobs</hi> day. Why, had not <hi>Eſau</hi> a day too? Yes, the day of my fathers mourning will be ſhortly: what then?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27.41</note> Why, then haue at my brother <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> I will kill, ſaith one Text, I will ſlay my brother <hi>Iacob;</hi> kill and ſlay are termes for <hi>Eſau. Rebecca</hi> heares of it, and cryes, ſhall I looſe both in one day? that is, the younger oppreſſed, and the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der accurſed; and <hi>Ieremie</hi> bringes in <hi>Rachell</hi> crying for her Children:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> cryed becauſe ſhee feared, <hi>Rachell</hi> wept becauſe they were not. And the Church our mother <hi>Rachel</hi>-like ſigheth and lamenteth in her Children <hi>non carnis neceſſitudinm, ſed fidei deſtructionem.</hi> Many amongſt vs are luke warme, and haſten to death as men ſtung with Aſpes, not fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:13106:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>their dying and are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any remorſe; and others are ſtriuing in their mothers wombe vnkindly like <hi>Benoni,</hi> Children of ſorrow, that bring her death for breeding them. If yee will yet ſo vnnaturally ſtriue, doe that which chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe, who when they haue bitte and ſcratcht a while, turne <hi>clamores</hi> in <hi>amores,</hi> and are friends againe. The great meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of times, made <hi>Iacobs</hi> afliction but a day; and will you nouriſh <hi>lites immortales</hi> immortall hatred? <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, <hi>morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium vtique mortalia ſunt opera;</hi> if you muſt die, let your contention firſt bee killed. See the longeſt and ſhorteſt daies of the yeare, the winter and ſummer, and you ſhall find the ſtormy winter dayes the ſhorteſt, becauſe they are the ſharpeſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 54.7.</note> All the Churches ſorrowes are reckoned but ten daies, and in <hi>Eſay</hi> for a moment in mine anger I haue ſmitten thee; Anger ſaith God, is not in me, if any appeare, you ſee it is but momentanie.</p>
            <p>Dayes of ſorrow haue many names in Scripture;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Ezechiel</hi> calls them <hi>dies pluuiae</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>raynie daies.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> calles them the daies of an hierling:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</note> Chriſt calles them <hi>dies tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum;</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> calles them daies of extremitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 24.</note> or daies of anguiſh: and in the booke of the Preacher,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.1.7.16.</note> 
               <hi>dies malos,</hi> euil daies and daies of vanity: and the prophets they ſpeake roughly; <hi>Eſay</hi> calles them <hi>dies inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 30.25. <hi>Eſay</hi> 34.8.</note> daies of ſlaughter, dayes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge and vengeance, daies wherein God exerciſeth his iudgements: and <hi>Amos</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them daies of a Tempeſt or Whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind: and <hi>Obadiah</hi> calles them daies of deſolation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obad.</hi> 1.</note> daies of ruine and deſtruction; and all meete together to make them daies of lamentation: and yet but a day, that is, a ſhort time, and paſsing quickly, and for the affliction of the daies, in the end of the world they ſhall be ſhortned, <hi>ob nimiam af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictionem,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour. And the laſt iudgement is called a day, either for the cleerenes, in that all euils now hidden ſhall then be manifeſted: or becauſe the Lord, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.28.</note> will make a ſhort ſum and abbreuiate quickly: and here this Prophet gathers vp into a ſumme, all <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>trouble into a day, one day, but it is <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es magnus,</hi> A great day.</p>
            <p>Great! why ſo?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.</note> for we haue heard a horrible noiſe, the voice of trembling, and not of peace, of mourning and lamenting, <hi>Alas, for this day is great.</hi> In compariſon, Great, in this verſe <hi>dies iſte,</hi> but in the eight verſe <hi>n die illo conteram iugum &amp; vincula,</hi> all will fit for vs anon: for this diſtreſſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> was great, when a Traytor offered to binde <hi>Iacob;</hi> but <hi>Iſrael</hi> heere did beare the yoake, and now was to be bound in yron bands; ſo <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was chained,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 25 7.</note> and this great ſhame and miſery the prophet afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand deſcribes, that men mourned, yea cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out like women in trauell, who keepe in their cryes as long as they can; at laſt do what they can, they will breake forth: and as in Cities ſet on fire by the enemie, ſome men runne vp and downe, others are amazed and ſtand ſtill, ſome looke pale, others whiſper, ſome ſhrike and crie out; ſo ſtood this people then afflicted, and afflicted in the day of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble; euery where <hi>Alas;</hi> and the ſorrowe was
<pb facs="tcp:13106:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>great, for this was a <hi>Great day:</hi> and now followeth the admiration; it was Great, <hi>for there was none like it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No? there was none like it! certainely there was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.</note> if <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpeake of captiuity: for what was harder then that of the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian bondage, infants taken from their mothers breaſts, and drowned in Riuers? all degrees of either ſex, oppreſſed with ſeruile workes and ſcourgings, things hard and heauie to be borne: yet in Aegypt they were bred, and grew miſerable by degrees; But for Maieſtie and State, ſuddenly to fal into diſtreſſe, ſhewes this (the higher vp the ſooner downe) and honors and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to be very baits of euill; but vnder a proud enemie to beare reproach! and to ſeeme reſerued for an euill day; thus <hi>dies magnus</hi> is become <hi>dies malus,</hi> in which ſaith God to <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 6.3.</note> theſe two things ſhall happen to thee;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 47.9.</note> loſſe of thy children, and widowhood, and both theſe will make a great lamenting, as when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was ſlain, then it was called <hi>Hadadimmon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.12.</note> in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Megiddon:</hi> then grewe vpon Iſraell
<pb facs="tcp:13106:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the euill day, when their good <hi>Ioſias</hi> was ſlain, who taking part with a wicked king, loſt his life and honour too; then was Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels glory ſhaken in that day, which <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> bewailes in his Lamentations, there was no ſorrow like that ſorrow, nor any day like this, <hi>non fuit ſimilis ei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, but the prophet doth not ſay, <hi>Non erit,</hi> there ſhall not be any day like this, but there hath not beene; for there ſhall bee a day, in which they ſhall-crie and houle; For as of the firſt day, it was ſaid, there hath beene none like it; ſuch is the laſt day, none ſhall be like it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ames</hi> 8.9.</note> as <hi>Amos</hi> the prophet ſaith, when the ſunne ſhall goe downe at noone, and it did ſo in our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours paſsion; and that day of ſorrow, of which the Fathers ſaid, <hi>Non erat dolor ſicut;</hi> is turned into a day of Redemption, of which it is truely ſaid, <hi>non erat ſimilis illi;</hi> for of this day <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Areopagite ſaid, <hi>Aut Deus naturae patitur aut mundi machina diſſoluitur:</hi> But yet the laſt day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thren.</hi> 1.12.</note> that day which is <hi>dies Domini,</hi> the day of our Lords comming, the day of iudgement, that is
<pb facs="tcp:13106:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>without all compariſon, for <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>non fuit ſimilis ei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Zoph.</hi> 1.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>nec erit:</hi> and <hi>Zophanias</hi> the prophet ſetts it downe for a ſtrange day, no Ephemerides can haue the like: Yea our bleſſed Saniour in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24 21.</note> ſets this ſtampe vpon it, <hi>Qulis non fuit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fiet,</hi> Firſt referred to the Iewes euerſion and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and then to that woſull ſubuerſion of wicked men in the day of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; which day he forewarnes to come like a thiefe: firſt ſpeedily and ſuddenly, and afterwards, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie with flaming fire,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.</note> rendering venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. This day is ſuch a day, that it may truely be ſaid, <hi>non fuit ſimilis ei, nec erit,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was ſeene ſuch a day, nor beſides that euer ſhall be.</p>
            <p>And now before I come to the Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, what <hi>Ieremies</hi> day is, marke what vſe ariſeth out of theſe three; the exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Alas;</hi> the Confirmation, <hi>for this day is great:</hi> and the ſpeech of wonder, <hi>none hath beene like it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt in the text is placed <hi>Alas,</hi> a <hi>Vae,</hi> the marke of ſorrow in the beginning, but yet
<pb facs="tcp:13106:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>the end is ſweet, for there is a <hi>liber abitur,</hi> or elſe the ſoule would faint, and to the ſoule it ſhewes, that God hath placed in <hi>veſtibu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo poenitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaies, yea bitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, as <hi>Anſelme</hi> calls it, <hi>ſit a mara poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia indiniduus con es etatis meae,</hi> and hee that performes it ſhall find it, though yet bitter repentance follow ſinne, after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance comes ſaluation, ſorrow firſt, and ioy will follow.</p>
            <p>Secondly, many euils and many aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities muſt be borne, therefore wee muſt haue patience, this repelles the darts of paine, and is a perpetuall document in matters of perplexitie, and only patience triumpheth ouer miſery.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God ſendeth ſorrowes for a checke, for in an eaſie life it is eaſie to doe amiſſe; therefore ſorrowes are like ſtrong Porters to ſhut the gates, where ſinnes would enter. Sorrow is a medicine and the ſmart of ſinne, and byting, cures whom it corrects, it preuents new dangers with dereſtation of the old diſeaſe. Auoid therefore thy liues bitter ſweets, for all thy
<pb facs="tcp:13106:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>worldly pleaſures are but fortunes flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and eaſie premiſes to bring thy ſoule to hard concluſions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, where Chriſt and all his Saints haue had their <hi>Alas</hi> and day of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and made their waie to higheſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours through thorny paſſages; why then, <hi>nudus nudum ſequere,</hi> nay rather armed with his life and death follow hard after the price, willing to change this earth for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, this life is the very froſty hardnes of al thy happineſſe and felicitie, and death will one day thaw and diſſolue and melt thy vanitie.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, theſe ſorrowes are but ſhort, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith momentany, and <hi>leues &amp; breues</hi> ſaith <hi>Athanaſius &amp; ideo leues quia bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues;</hi> ſhort it is indeede that is ended in a day; and it is much comfort, when heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is but for a night and ioy commeth in the morning.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, although miſery hath her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and the end of one aduerſitie be the beginning of another, yet none can bee greater then a ſtate and kingdome, then
<pb facs="tcp:13106:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>maieſtie it ſelfe to be caſt into miſery, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> was in his day: which may ſhew Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates thus much, that Kings and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and famous Cities haue their dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes; and the more happie in libertie is the more wretched in danger; mariner's call fortune a tempeſt, and a great fortune is a great tempeſt, and there we haue neede of ſtrength and councell too; if therefore thou haſt waſted the day in foule wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, prouide that at night thou maiſt be in the hauen.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, the day is great, and none like it, for though there ſhall be none like that day of iudgement, yet ſome will date to deſire not <hi>diem magnum,</hi> but <hi>diem malum,</hi> as in <hi>Amos,</hi> and the very daie of Chriſt with ſuch a face, as if they would out-face the Iudge: Thus doth ſinne put on a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots fore-head, and in her euils is become impudent, that if there were not a daie wherein <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhould be honoured, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery proude Tyrant ouerturned; if death were not moderator to pull them hence, <hi>obtorto collo,</hi> as the proucrbe is, there are
<pb facs="tcp:13106:20"/>ſome that would liue alone, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſine rege, ſine lege,</hi> yea, and <hi>ſine grege</hi> too, that is, without all humane ſocietie. Well, theſe may haue their day, <hi>diem ſuum; viz.</hi> a day of their owne making, but when the daie ſhall come, that ſheepe and Goates ſhall be diuided, that day ſhall reforme all and turn good mens faſting into feaſting, and right all wrongs; but for the while t'is heauie to beare, it is a daie, a daie and none like it; tell plainelie then, what daie is it?</p>
            <p>It is the time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble:</p>
            <p>Time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble! what's this? Indeede this is the day, this fift of Auguſt, wherein our <hi>Iacob</hi> was troubled, and I did but hold you in ſuſpenſe a while, it was our owne cauſe, and came very neere vs, while I ſpake of Iſraell and that ſtate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the verſe, <hi>iam tua res agitur, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I will draw away the veyle, and ſpeake plainely: Great was the Alas, the ſignes, and cauſe of ſorrow, a heauie day, and none like it: A king that is <hi>alti ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis decus,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaid of <hi>Marcella,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>a King that holds it nobility, <hi>clarum eſſe virtutibus,</hi> as the ſame father ſaith, <hi>qui benig nitate potius quam ſeueritate exigit reuerenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> a king, the glory of theſe times, the moſt noble of all his progenitors; <hi>Henricus ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, regna Iacobus:</hi> ſuch a king to wreſtle for life in the gripes of a Traytor; this time was the time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble, and in ſo great a matter, that we may running reade, as <hi>Abacuc</hi> ſaid, or hearing diſcerne, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes: and to proceede orderly; in theſe words I find three things principally to treate of, and they are:</p>
            <p>Firſt the perſon diſtreſſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the name of it, Tribulation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the continuance, it laſteth but for a time.</p>
            <p>The perſon, whoſe diſtreſſe <hi>Ieremy</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes; and the text ſaith, it was <hi>Iacobs:</hi> but how can this be <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble? <hi>Iacobs</hi> head now did not ake, for true it is, <hi>Iacob</hi> was dead before this time about one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fiue hundred yeare; how may it then be <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble? The Scripture ſhewes that <hi>Iacob</hi> is <hi>populus dei,</hi> and Saint <hi>Ierome</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:21"/>ſaith, <hi>duodecim tribus intellige;</hi> by theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the poſterity too, for all is but <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> becauſe all this people deſcended from him.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore it is ſet for the honour of his name, <hi>memoria iuſti in aeternum, Pſal.</hi> 112. for <hi>Iacob</hi> was a ſincere hearted man, plaine, and of true dealing, a man very deere to God, as appeared by his ſtory; and God brings their fathers name to remembrance for his great honour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Iacobs</hi> life was an afflicted life, and therfore fitter to haue this word tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ioyned to it; and this prophet is, ſaith <hi>Ierome, in verbis ſimplex &amp; facilis, in maieſtate ſenſuum proſundiſsimus,</hi> and fits his wordes to the perſon, <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Jacob</hi> had a ſpeciall trouble, which neuer any had in ſuch a kind; and there muſt be ſomething in him to anſwer to his name, <hi>Iacob</hi> a wreſtler, a ſupplanter, like one that in wreſtling trippes vp ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heeles, a ſtriuer and a great preuailer, a man that wreſtled with God, and held an Angell ſo faſt, that he would not let
<pb facs="tcp:13106:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>him goe without a bleſsing; and in his mothers wombe hee was forced to wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle for his life with rough <hi>Eſau:</hi> and in <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero</hi> there he was too weake, his brother preuailed, and got before him, and was borne firſt, but yet <hi>Iacob</hi> held him by the heele, and thereupon had his name, for <hi>Iacob</hi> is <hi>calcaneum</hi> as <hi>Pagnine</hi> notes; but <hi>ab vtero,</hi> then <hi>Iacob</hi> was the ſtronger, and the elder ſerued the younger, <hi>non obediendo ſed perſequendo,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> hee ſerued him many a cruell touch, as the prouerbe is.</p>
            <p>And yet did <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtle; with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wraſtlings haue I wraſtled with my ſiſter, ſaith <hi>Rachell,</hi> when ſhee obtained a ſonne, and called him <hi>Nephthali,</hi> and, ſaith ſhe, I haue preuailed. And ſo might <hi>Iacob</hi> ſay, with excellent wraſtlings haue I wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtled, with my brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and I haue preuailed: indeed excellent wraſtlings and for excellent things, for a birth-right, and a bleſsing too, and hee may ſay, I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed, for he gat them both, and ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> And may not our renowned <hi>Iacobus,</hi> our ſoueraigne King,
<pb facs="tcp:13106:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>our Patriarch, from whoſe face ſhines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but grace and mercy; may not he ſay with excellent wreſtlings, and vehement wreſtlings haue I wreſtled, with a Traytor hand to hand, foote to foote, with gripe for gripe, and I haue preuailed? <hi>Alas, for this day is great, none like it, for it was the time of our Iacobs trouble.</hi> And now I come to that which in order is next, the time requires it, and I know you expect it: the trouble wherein our ſoueraigne was in that vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Conſpiracy of <hi>Gowries</hi> againſt his Maieſties life and honour, againſt the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull happineſſe of theſe kingdomes, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in his Maieſties moſt royall perſon, againſt the now enioyed ioyes of euerie true-hearted ſubiect, a treaſon odious to God and men, infamous to the perſons, and the deliuerance therefrom, the greateſt glory to God that any poore ſinners may aſcribe. In which matter theſe things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be omitted, but neceſſarily be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Authors and Actors of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the action it ſelfe, namely to kill the king.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thirdly, the manner of doing it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the contention or wreſtling, with the time it endured.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>miraculum ſalutis,</hi> the wonder of deliuerance. All which ſhew it was a ſad and heauie time. <hi>Alas this is a great day, none was like it, it was the very time of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs trouble:</hi> and ſo can <hi>Iacob</hi> tell beſt, how he was affected when hee was worſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
            <p>And now firſt of the Authours and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this ſaddeſt (thankes be to God for it) not Tragedy, that ends with killing of kings: but through Gods mercie a <hi>tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comedia,</hi> for though the beginning be ſad, yet it had a ioyfull end.</p>
            <p>I would ſpare the name for the hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of the fault,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 16.4.</note> with king <hi>Dauids ne memorentur nomina eorum inter labia mea</hi> and had rather hide then blaze a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Fact. And yet in the names, this comfort the innocent of that name may haue, that as of others vertues a man may conceiue much ioy, but winne no glorie to himſelfe; ſo of anothers fault
<pb facs="tcp:13106:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may conceiue a griefe, but take no ſhame; for where the fault is, there the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and ſhame muſt light.</p>
            <p>But truth enforceth to expreſſe the name of <hi>Gowries,</hi> and I ſhould prooue a falſe and faithles ſeruant, to tender more the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders names, then they would tender my Maſters life. <hi>Gowry,</hi> and an Earle, <hi>Comes principis,</hi> marke how iuſtly King <hi>Dauids</hi> and king <hi>Iames</hi> his cauſe agreeth; he ſaith, If it had beene thou mine enemie, that hadſt done me this diſhonour, I could wel haue borne it; and this ſaying is referred vnto <hi>Iudas</hi> that betraied Chriſt, from whom all Traytors are called <hi>Iudaſſes:</hi> from an enemie? I could then haue borne it: But it was thou my <hi>Comes,</hi> my companion and a familiar friend,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 55.12.</note> which did eate at my Table; yea to whom our King had giuen againe his forfeited eſtate, and made him and them a Table: that is, enriched, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, benefited, honoured them; and a companion, a friend, a <hi>Comes</hi> to doe thus? It is much, yet it is no new thing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour would rather be betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:13106:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a Diſciple, then any other, as S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>voluit deſeri, voluit prodi, voluit ab apoſtolo tradi, vt tu a ſocio tuo proditus mode ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te feras tuum erraſse iudicium, tuum periiſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium:</hi> Indeede gifts may bee giuen for neceſsitie, but loue is to be beſtowed with iudgement. No great hurt is it, yet griefe it is, to conferre vpon vnthankful perſons; but benefits turned into weapons, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the giuer is griefe and danger too, as <hi>Ignatius Epiſtola ad Romanos</hi> ſaid he was bound by beaſts, <hi>qui ex beneficiis peiores fiunt,</hi> that is, the better you vſe them, the worſe they are. But let his greatneſſe goe, and ſee his confidence: For this Earle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene addicted to charmes and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancie, and being ſlaine, had in his pocket a patchment of magicall characters found, which he euer carried with him, as his preſeruatiue from danger: belike thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelfe ſafer vnder the diuels witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, then to be guarded with the grace of God. And this was apparant for one ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his charmes, that though he were thruſt through at the verie heart, yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:13106:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>bled, but when the Characters were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, his blood guſht out abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; a wretched man, a miſerable confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Yea but to make his Table the ſnare, and his owne houſe the ſlaughter-place, is barbarous and ignoble; and for any man to turne hoſpitality into hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is monſtrous; ſo <hi>Lycaon</hi> would haue killed <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and for falſe turning, was turned into a Wolfe: for by the lawes of humanity all hate ſhould there haue ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yea that houſe ſhould rather haue bin a harbor againſt violence, and a ſanctuary eſpecially for a ſacred perſon, then to make it the priſon of ſo free a king, and the ſhambles for Soueraignty: How true is that ſaying?<note place="margin">Jerom. de vita Nalchi.</note> 
               <hi>ouis, quae de ouilibus egreditur, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi ſtatim morſib. patet,</hi> the innocent minde that thinkes no harme, is ſooneſt brought to danger. See if it would not trouble <hi>Iacob</hi> to be thus dealt with by a Companion, a <hi>Comes principis,</hi> by a perſon honoured with his Maieſties preſence, and that any nature ſhould againſt the lawes of nature there intend his hurt, whom he ought to helpe,
<pb facs="tcp:13106:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Alas, it was a great day to fall into ſuch hands, none was like it, it was the time of</hi> IACOBS <hi>trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the deſperate Actor was the Earles brother, <hi>frater quaſi fere alter,</hi> almoſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith <hi>Iſidorus;</hi> nay this <hi>Alexander</hi> was a brother, that is as badde and ſomewhat worſe; yea they were brothers indeede,<note place="margin">Geneſ <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>fratres in malo,</hi> as the Patriarch <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leuie,</hi> curſed be their wrath, for it was fierce, and their rage, for it was cruell: goe on good Patriarch ſtill, and ſay, into their ſecret let not my ſoule come, nor <hi>Iacobs</hi> life into their cloſets. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larion</hi> the Eremite ſaid of the Diuell,<note place="margin">Ierom. in vita eius.</note> 
               <hi>in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melo atque in vulpecula vnus &amp; idem es diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> Whether in an Earle, or whether in a Brother, thou art but one Traytor, yet ſee how this Foxe carries his taile, I meane the end of his Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, hee ſpeakes ſo faire with lowly wordes, and lookes, with cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie neuer lower ducking; I ſhould ſay, with duetie downe to the ground: A verie Marke of TREASON; ſo ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:13106:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Italian prouerbe, He that vſeth mee better then he was wont, will me betray: but let the Hebrew prophet ſpeake in his diſcouerie of a Traytor: He lieth in waite ſecretly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.7.8.</note> as a Lion in his Denne; this ſet teth out the elder Brother, for he kept home, and would not be ſeene in it; he fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth downe and humbleth himſelfe, to make the ſimple fall by his might; and this was the <hi>Alexander</hi> of this treaſon, by guiles and wiles to entrappe a harmeleſſe breſt, and draw it into danger.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in him I obſerue the proude and ſcornful heart of a Traytor, that when he had cloſed and locked in his Soueraign in a ſtraight roome, ſo vnmindfull was he of Maieſtie, he changed his former faire wordes into foule deeds, clapt on his hatte, ſwearing and ſtaring in the face of his king; menacing and threatning him, now with hands, and words and bands, whom not long ſince he ſolicited with all duety and mediation, to haue beene one of his Maieſties Chamber. It may be a warning to Princes, whom they entertaine, and
<pb facs="tcp:13106:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>how they admit of any vnhallowed hands to come neere where Maieſtie dwels. Thus was our moſt noble Patriarch ſhut vp, and brought into trouble for the time; the Text ſaies, <hi>it was the time of Iacobs trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And well might this be called ſo, for the action was to kill the king; this was the end, like the diuels <hi>quaerens quem deuoret,</hi> for deſtroying is his end. A ſubiect to kill his king! <hi>Si omnia membra corporis in linguas verterentur,</hi> to vſe Saint <hi>Ieromes</hi> words,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3 15.</note> how ſhould I ſpeake out this euill? Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, he that hateth his brother, is a Man-ſlayer, and no Man-ſlayer hath part in the kingdome of God: where then ſhall hee be thrown, but like a dogge vpon a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, that killes his king; without ſhall be dogs as in the Reuelation, &amp; inchanters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.15.</note> &amp; murtherers, &amp; who ſo loueth or ſpeaketh lies; &amp; this was compaſſed all by lying. In <hi>Matth.</hi> our Sauior ſaith,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> He that calleth his brother (foole) in wrath ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſhal be in danger of hell fire. To kill a man wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully &amp; deſperatly, is homicide,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 9.31.</note> to kil a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parricide: had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace which ſlew
<pb facs="tcp:13106:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maſter? ſhall he haue peace that murthers the Lords annointed? Our law doth well to make it treaſon for a ſeruant to kill his Maſter, a wife the husband, a Clerke his Prelate or Superiour, or any other ſuch as haueciuil rule and ſoueraignty ouer them; and ſhall this king-killing trade ſet vp, and now warranted by that Romiſh blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucker, become no ſinne but merite? I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remember a wittie tale of a foole, walking farre from home (as many fooles doe) a ſhrewd fellow of the houſe met him, and would haue ſet him home, and ſcar'd him much, and ieſtingly threatned to kill him: the foole in earneſt told his Maſter; O Maſter, ſuch a one wil kill me: kill thee ſaith his Maſter! if he kill thee I'le hange him next day after. Nay rather (ſaith the foole) hang him a day before, and then I ſhall be ſafe. I wiſh, I heartily pray, that al ſuch as beare that mind, to drinke inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, ſacred blood, the blood of Princes, and of States (if they conuert not) that they might all be hang'd a day before they ſpill it. And that yet at laſt his Maieſty
<pb facs="tcp:13106:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo well experienced of the malice of that blood-thirſty generation, would as hee hath well begunne, either vtterly baniſh theſe Romiſh Prieſts and Ieſuites; and if they will not away, but ſtill abuſe his mercy, as they be taken to hang the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. We may preach here and elſe where, till our hearts ake; but if they may maſſe it, and reconcile in ſecret as they doe, late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I feare, will ouertake the kingdome, and the States great ſuffrance may perhaps at laſt, againſt their willes, prooue good ſubiects annoyance: Therefore you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, I exhort you in the Lord, as you tender the life of the king, the peace of the ſtate, and the common good, fetch theſe ſnakes out of their holes.</p>
            <p>But me thinkes I heare ſome ſay, wee apprehend, we commit them, we do what we can, and what comes of it? ther's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done; it is a ſore ſpeech this, yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill you the law, goe on in the right way; if they ſcape ſtill, yet take thoſe Foxes ſtil, for feare of an euill day: for this <hi>I</hi> knowe by much experience, if there be any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb facs="tcp:13106:27"/>in the world, it is the fortune of the worſt men euer to ſcape puniſhment; but this kind of Romiſh ſpider firſt weaues his web in corners, but after will hang vp (if firſt they hang not him) his worke in Kings houſes, if they take not heed. <hi>Miſeri ſunt principes, ſi intelligant ſua mala</hi> (ſaid lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) <hi>miſeriores verò ſi non intelligant.</hi> To warne them of dangers is our office, if we forbeare it, who ſhall doe it? and in theſe diſtaſtfull times, when at many mens hands the truth may hardly bee indured, and wretches preſume though not to ſtrike and kill, yet with their tongues to throw ſtones at Maieſtie. <hi>Lycophron</hi> called Iuno <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is invulnerable,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de. Valentiniano.</note> not that maieſty cannot, but that it ought not to be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. To take away an Emperours life is <hi>Soleme mundo tollere</hi> to put out the Sunne; and to kill our King is <hi>Lucernam Britanniae extinguere,</hi> to quench the life and light of Britanny.</p>
            <p>Conſider next the manner of this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Firſt by deuiſe, by fraud and lyes to draw his credulous ſoule to daunger
<pb facs="tcp:13106:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>credulas animas maliioqua lingua diſſociat</hi> a falſe and lying tongue,<note place="margin">Ierom. ad Celantian.</note> diſſeuers and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiles the Credulous. Well; hee leades the King and miſleads him, lockes euery dore and Aenigmatically ſayes, I warrant you hee is ſafe and faſt enough: well; nay it is very ill, for he ſhuttes vp an armed man there, then with oathes and bloudy threats telles him he muſt now die, chargeth his innocent maieſtie, with the death of his father, who was iudged by their Law long before, and that in his maieſties mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority. Yet is there no remedy, for al that, it is he muſt die; then pulles he out that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers dagger, and ſets it to his ſacred breſt, beginnes to triumph ouer his Lord, offers to bind his King in bands; <hi>Alas, this day was great, none was like it, this was the time of Iacobs Trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if euer <hi>Iacob</hi> was a wraſtler, hee muſt now wraſtle for his life, and ſo hee did, and by force helde him, who by fraud deceiued him, and in that ſtrife was heard to call, and (like that moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Patriarch that helde <hi>Eſau</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:13106:28"/>the heele) he ſupplanted this rough-han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and tough-hearted Traytor.</p>
            <p>The Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh: that is, when the ſoule is in a ſtrait, it is here expreſſed tribulation: and this <hi>tribulus</hi> or <hi>tribulum,</hi> the firſt is a thorne, the other a flaile, that breakes out the corne, both painefull to endure; of the firſt the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>conuerſus ſum in aerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, dum configitur ſpina,</hi> where a thorne is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened in the fleſh, it is an inward and a rankling ſorrow: ſo may our king haue ſaid, <hi>conuerſus ſum,</hi> and vnleſſe it had beene <hi>Deus in adiutorium,</hi> he might haue ſaid <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus ſum. S. Bernard</hi> ſaith <hi>Spina malus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus, malus Miniſter, Apostata diſcipulus, falſus frater, ſpina vicinus malus,</hi> ſuch badde neighbours had hee, but bleſſed bee the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that ſuffered not this thorne, <hi>vt infigatur,</hi> that it ſhould pierce him; let the fire of the Lord fal among ſuch thorns and conſume them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tribulum</hi> is a flaile; and here was <hi>Iacob</hi> like good corne on the floore, <hi>in area contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus &amp; ab omni humana confidentia ventilatus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>threſhed in the floore, and winnowed from all worldly hopes or confidence; <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num tritici in area;</hi> nay rather <hi>agnus in crucis ara:</hi> a Lambe for ſacrifice, ſauing in the hands of a Butcher, not a Sacrificer. O <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> God, and Iſraels guide; the fierie pillar and the daies cloud, if God had not helped now (may Iſraell now ſay) if God had not beene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Maſter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and a mightie defence in that great and euill day, <hi>Iacob</hi> might ſay, I ſhould haue periſhed in my trouble; a great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the time, and it was but a time, as my text inferreth.</p>
            <p>The time. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith to euery worke vnder heauen there is an appointed time, but amongſt all thoſe workes he reckons not this time; there ſhould be no time to aſſault Maieſtie, neuer ſuch a time: Well, then was a time of this trouble, and it had his time, and here it is called a Day; yet it was a day almoſt to night here, ere it could bee quieted: But marke this one thing how God reſtraines wicked men in their worſt euils, conſtraines fury to yeeld;
<pb facs="tcp:13106:29"/>and keepes the Diuell in chaines, whoſe malice and miſchiefe may endure but for a little time; yet the ſhorter the time is, the ſharper is his furie, as Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Quanto minus de tempore anguſtatur, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to magis ad crudelitatem extenditur,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely as the diuell hath a name, <hi>Extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans,</hi> that is a deſtroyer: ſo are they to bee called that partake of the Diuels nature: the Sybill ſaid of Chriſt, that when hee ſhould come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſhall diſſolue the wicked Oracles, and breake the violent bands: and this verie worke of Chriſt appeared herein, to dant the heart, and daube vp the mouth of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed oaths, &amp; parted thoſe hands of bands, reſcued his Maieſties life from that ſad and heauie houre, which we had found if hee had felt it; ſo that now it is certainely a great day; great then in the greatneſſe of the euils (the time of <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble) and now greater in the ioy of his Maieſties moſt happy deliuerance; great trouble, <hi>Sed tamen liberabitur,</hi> but yet he ſhal be deliuered from it. And ſo I come to that which I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Miraculum ſalutis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In which I obſerue theſe three things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Authour of this deliuerance; God onely, and how he ſhewed himſelfe in it:</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Iacobs</hi> vertue, conſiſting in theſe two:
<list>
                  <item>1. The innocency of his heart, which euer carries comfort and defence.</item>
                  <item>2. Greatneſſe of minde, valour and magnanimity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the inſtruments of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, by whom though God doe many things miraculouſly, yet ſuch is his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo euident for our ſakes, that he ſaues by meanes, and not by miracles.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God was the Authour of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance; and in it the head of all mercie is, <hi>Ero tecum;</hi> and the promiſe, <hi>cum ipſo ſum in tribulatione,</hi> I am with him in trouble: this being of God with faithfull men, is the life of al their deliuerance, their ſumm of comfort, <hi>fons benedictionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calles it. It was ſaid of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the Lord was with him, and made all things to proſper in his handes, foure times in one
<pb facs="tcp:13106:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>chapter, <hi>erat Dominus cum Ioſeph,</hi> and being ſhut vp in the priſon, the Lord was with him: he is euery where, <hi>per eſſentiam,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> but with his ſeruants he is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, with them <hi>per habitationis gratiam.</hi> In Exodus the Lord comforts <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.12.</note> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I will be with thee, and to <hi>Ioſuah.</hi> the Lord ſpeaketh; feare not <hi>Ioſua,</hi> be ſtrong and of good courage,<note place="margin">Joſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> there ſhall not a man be able to withſtand thee all the daies of thy life; as I was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo will I bee with thee. And when Iuda ſhould go vp to warre,<note place="margin">Iud. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dominus erat cum Iuda;</hi> if a man can get the Lord his God with him, he is ſafe enough, though he be encloſed with walls and lockes, and barres, becauſe God is <hi>extra omnia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>ſed non excluſus: intra omnia, ſed non incluſus,</hi> without, yet not excluded, within, and not ſhut vp; and ſo it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his mercy in this day. <hi>Salomon</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prayeth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.57.</note> that God would he with him as he was with their fathers; that he leaue them not, nor forſake them. And it is an excellent praier for the young Prince, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſhould be in any ſtrait, as his father
<pb facs="tcp:13106:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>was (which God forbid) he might pray that God would be with him, as he was with his father in the day of his trouble, &amp; in the very houre of tentation to deliuer him:</p>
            <p>But how was God with their fathers? <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibiliter, ineffabiliter, admirabiliter,</hi> How thus? for he works &amp; is not ſeene: he ſtirred vp the ſpirit of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſtrengthned him, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> mine armes ſhall breake a Bowe of ſteele: inuiſibly he wrought in that others heart, that was placed there to kill him, that at the ſight of the king his heart failed, his tongue faultred, his hands ſhooke, all his body tremble, and had neither hart or any power to hurt, to helpe perhaps, but not able to hurt: Is not this to ſtop the Lions mouthes? he wrought inuiſibly in the heart of that deſperate <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Ruthwen,</hi> the Earles brother, that was at firſt as fierce as a Tyger or a Beare, that the wordes of his Maieſtie made him relent, and conſider and reſpite till hee might talke with the Earle his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but after that, came againe, bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily reſolued to bee imbrewde; yet then
<pb facs="tcp:13106:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>God was with him, as with the Patriarch <hi>Iacob</hi> in Aegypt, that yron ſorrow; and as he was with <hi>Jonas</hi> in the Whales belly, and kept him from conſuming. But if you aske me, how was he with him? I can but ſay <hi>ineffabiliter,</hi> I cannot tel how to vtter it: Nay more, he was with him <hi>admirabiliter;</hi> How's that? a preſent helpe in trouble, at euery ſtabbe, at euery gripe, at euery aſſault a rocke of ſtone, a refuge, a defence, and therefore bleſſed be the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and bleſſed be he that hath the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> for his helpe, and whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, which onely doth great things, and hee is wonderfull among the kings of the earth, and ſo he was with our king in this day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I noted the kings vertue in this conflict; the firſt is innocency, which euery where carries with it comfort and defence. It was a noble ſpeach of <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> king of Arragon, being aduiſed to take ſome care of his perſon, where, and how he walked priuately, anſwered, <hi>Satis munitus eſt, qui bonam habet conſcientiam;</hi> yea this is a
<pb facs="tcp:13106:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>good armour for the ſoule, yet ſometime the body wants it; a good conſcience is a continuall feaſt indeed, and nothing can keepe in true peace your conſcience, but your innocence.</p>
            <p>Another vertue was the magnanimity of <hi>Iacob,</hi> which is certainely a vertue roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and ſuffers not the mind to be daunted with any aduerſities; no feares, no rumors nor euill tidings, ſhall make him quake,<note place="margin">Pſalm, <hi>112.</hi>
               </note> who ſtandeth in the Lord; and this is ſuch a vertue as hath beene annexed to the Crowne, that kings ſhould be magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; <hi>Salomon</hi> fetcheth an argument of mercy from Gods omnipotency, <hi>miſereris omnium qui omnia potes,</hi> thou haſt mercy on all, becauſe thou art Almighty, and noble Kings are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not ſo much for bountie as for mercie Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith <hi>procul abeſt a magnanimis cupiditas vltionis,</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant natures neuer reuenge: it is for wolues and Beares, for cowards to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, <hi>&amp; quaecunque minor nobilitate fera eſt,</hi> ſaith the Poet. As God therefore prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Dauid</hi> with Lions and Beares, and then
<pb facs="tcp:13106:32"/>brought him forth againſt the Philiſtim; and armed <hi>Iob,</hi> giuing him as one ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Patriarchicall ſoule,<note place="margin">Origin.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and valiant to endure al ſorrow that might come; ſo did the almighty bleſſe our holy King, with a ſpeech, Spirit, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſtrength and courage, to reſiſt his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, and <hi>Iacob</hi> like, to wraſtle for the bleſſing which now his eyes doe ſee and wee enioy.</p>
            <p>The third thing is the meanes which God vſed for his Maieſties Deliuerance, for though God doth many things mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly, yet makes he not a man, to fly out of a caſement like a bird, but ordereth by high prouidence, things below, and men and meanes, in the very extremity he directeth, where the danger is. That cloſe by the windows, his ownſe uants ſhould paſſe where his Maieſtie was ſtriuing; they heard his call, went vp and found their Lord in the graſpe of a Traytor, but the Traytor ouer-graſped that hee could not hurt. By a noble ſeruant of his were firſt the very wreathes of this Serpent vntwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
<pb facs="tcp:13106:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Alexander of miſchiefe turned out to his curſed but deſerued end; that as he ſhewed no mercy; ſo periſhing hee called for none from God, in whoſe hand onely mercy was. <hi>Euripides</hi> ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> al men may know the calamities of Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For yet all <hi>Iacobs</hi> Trouble was not ouer paſt. But now the olde ſerpent, with ſeuen other ſpirits as ill as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, came vp to the place armed, aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Maieſties. fower defendants where with much ſtrife and doubtfull victory, at laſt it pleaſed God, to ſend the Earle his hire, and the reſt vanquiſhed to bee throwne downe head-long. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſaide <hi>Ignatius ad Magneſianos Nemo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus nemanſit: qui ſe contra potiores extu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit,</hi> his Maieſtie now, had a little brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing giuen him, and like a religious and holy King vpon his knees in the flore, where his enemie lay dead before him, gaue harty thankes to God for ſo great a mercy. And this; and thus, <hi>was the time of Iacobs Trouble.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13106:33"/>Trouble? yea, <hi>But he ſhall be deliuered from it,</hi> ſaith God, and here he performed it; and hitherto as the day requireth, I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the trouble which concerned <hi>Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſolation of <hi>Iacob</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>Sed tamen liberabitur,</hi> Vnſpeakeable is the ioy of deliuerance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1.</note> it ſo opens the heart, and makes them ſing that finde it. And ſo did the Iſraelites ſing, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the men, and <hi>Miriam</hi> and the women with Timbrels, <hi>quia fecit Dominus magnificè,</hi> the Lord hath triumphed gloriouſly, he ſaued them, and deſtroyed their enemies, <hi>fecit magnificè,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> he did valiantly: and <hi>Deborah</hi> made a ſong, when God deliuered Iſraell from the hand of <hi>Siſera</hi> Captaine of the Hoſt of <hi>Iabin,</hi> king of Canaan; and it is for a glorious victory, a moſt noble ſong: thus the Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> were moſt of them compoſed, and are thankeſgiuings vnto God: How did the three children ſing in the flaming Furnace? and <hi>Ionas</hi> pray and praiſe God deliuered from the whale?<note place="margin">Ion. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> what hart can expreſſe the ioy of the Iewes deliuered from <hi>Haman?</hi> not one but all
<pb facs="tcp:13106:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be deſtroyed, and how mercifully God did turne the deſtruction vpon the deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as he did in this day: by theſe you may ſee, what ioy comes with this <hi>Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is like Gods Angell that comforted Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and bad him not to feare, but be bolde, the Lord ſhall ſtand by thee: or like the Angels touch, that made all S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> chaines fall off at once: And I ſay that any that hath knowne the worlds malice, the depth of Satan, the rage of his Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, may ſay with the holy prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> I was in woſull miſerie, and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered me: what is hee in his life, to whom deliuerance, at one time or other, hath not beene ſweete?</p>
            <p>But this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a future time, a promiſe, <hi>He ſhall be deliuered, verbum dulce ſuper mel &amp; fauum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> yea but when? <hi>quando duplicantur late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res tunc venit Moſes,</hi> not now, nor yet, but in the time of his trouble: So in the Pſalme, <hi>Jnuoca me in die tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis &amp; ego liberabo te,</hi> in the time
<pb facs="tcp:13106:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>of thy trouble, in thy greateſt anguiſh and extremity, for then God ſhewes himſelfe like Chriſt, who ſlept til his Diſciples were almoſt drowned, and then rebukes, &amp;c. and ſuſpends his mercy to take thee out like <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was ſinking, he cryed then, and Chriſt then preſently reſcued him. When there is but a ſteppe betweene thee and death, then God deliuereth, then is his time.</p>
            <p>And this doth comfort much to think that we haue God a looker on, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; yea a Maſter and a Moderator in the matter, that things are gouerned, not by Fate and Conſtellations, but by heauenly Prouidence, which ſlumbers not.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt haue patience, to tarrie Gods leiſure; there is no appointing his wiſedome the time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith.</hi> 8.16.</note> as <hi>Iudith</hi> notably ſaid to the Elders of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to tarry fiue daies; ſaith ſhee, What? will ye binde his Councel,<note place="margin">Abac. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> or ſet the Lord a time? nay rather as <hi>Abacuc</hi> aduiſeth; if the viſion come not, tarrie thou, if it ſpeake not, yet waite; for it ſhall ſpeake in
<pb facs="tcp:13106:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>his appointed time, and the Lorde will humble fleſh and blood, and deferre his comforts to make them ſweeter, <hi>Si differt Deus ſua dona, commendat non negat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Anguſh.</hi> and S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>delicata eſt diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na conſobatio, &amp; non datur admittentibus alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> it is a ſweete mercy to be deliuered, and he that will haue it, muſt only looke to God, and in this patience and hopefull expecting muſt euery good man poſſeſſe his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt then hope moſt, where his reaſon is leaſt and this is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mans part; for what reaſon had <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to hope for <hi>Iſaac</hi> at thoſe yeares? If as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> he had not beleeued and hoped, without fixing his heart vpon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: or <hi>Dauid</hi> euer to haue worne the Crowne, if he had bent to reaſon: And what reaſon had <hi>Iacob</hi> in this day to hope, but that faith like <hi>Deborabs</hi> ſoule, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth valiantly and endureth like <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> as ſeeing him which is inuiſible.</p>
            <p>The third thing which I noted in this <hi>(liberabitur)</hi> is, That <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt not bee
<pb facs="tcp:13106:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>weake-handed nor faint-hearted, to droup and caſt away his confidence, but valiant and couragious, and ſo expect the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: for this cauſe did the Angell ſay to <hi>Gedeon,</hi> goe in this thy might thou valiant man. Kings and Princes be called Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, but yet ſuch as neede ſaluation, and they that ſaue others, the Lord will ſaue them: But if there be any king, or noble, or Iudge, or Prelate, or potentate, that abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his power, and will not ſaue ſuch as are oppreſſed, the Lord will leaue ſuch in their enemies hands; and as they haue no care to comfort others: ſo GOD in their times of trouble ſhall leaue them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, and this ſhall be their iuſt porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe kind of men are endued with a more noble ſpirit, not for their owne ſakes ſo much as for others: <hi>Dauid</hi> had a heart like a lion, <hi>Sampſon</hi> rends a lion in peeces, and after ſaues his people; and that people of Iſraell, not onely in their Rulers had a bleſsing of mightie and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant men, but in inferiours alſo, to ſhew that from GOD commeth alſo the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:13106:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ornaments of Nobilitie, and they are certainely moſt Noble, that are moſt Faithfull, and they moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant that are moſt vertuous.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Iacob</hi> that euer was, faieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.40.</note> I endured, &amp;c. and then reckons his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; and the laſt, and all muſt endure till they receiue the promiſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 36.5.</note> for <hi>Iob</hi> that ſuffered heauie things was tolde by <hi>Elihu,</hi> that the mightie God caſteth away none that is mightie and valiant of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is to ſhew, what is implyed in this worde IACOB; and this will make vp the application, and ſheweth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriarches life was a verie troubleſome life, full of difficultie, daunger, diſtreſſe; hearts griefe amongſt his children, and yet GOD made a ſweete and bleſſed ende with him, and deliuered him from all, ſent him downe into Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, yea went with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.4.</note> 
               <hi>Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam tecum in Aegyptum,</hi> there hee ſawe
<pb facs="tcp:13106:36"/>
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his fruit full bough, there he bleſſed his ſonnes, there he died and gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>undement of his bones, that is, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying their <hi>liberahitur,</hi> iſraell ſhall be deliuered.</p>
            <p>But here <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtandes for a whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to whom <hi>Jeremy</hi> for their ſinne threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Captiuity and makes a deſcription of a ſaid and ruth full day, wherein they ſhall looke with gaſlly and amazed looks one vpon another, pale faced and heauie hearted, when this day ſhall come, a great day, a day of ſorrow, the day of wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and miſerie, neuer day like it; a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſetled in a glorious ſtate, thought neuer to be remoued, but they ſhall haue their day, and ſo had Ieruſalem in Chriſts time her day. <hi>O ſicognouiſſes, &amp;c.</hi> and that day was her day, and time of trouble.</p>
            <p>Let vs looke vpon our ſelues; wee ſtand now, wee may fall, wee are at peace, but there can be no ſecurity, yron and clay legs will not, nor can not beare vp the biazen thighes, the golden lead, and ſiluer body; the bribery and prowling, the
<pb facs="tcp:13106:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>oppreſsion and cries of the oppreſſed, the parking in of beaſts, and depopulating Townes, to ſhut out Chriſtians, the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of iuſtice, the death of godly zeale, the contempt of lawes, and all good order, wil bring a day of trouble vpon <hi>Iacob,</hi> that is vpon this kingdome, which God yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes in great mercie, to make <hi>Iacob</hi> and euerie <hi>Iacob</hi> to bethinke themſelues, and not to melt away in worldly pleaſures: for this is true, they that bath themſelues in pleaſure and in worldly ioy, it makes the manlieſt heart to melt away; and I haue heard it, and read it often, and in my life haue ſeene it, that there are many haue beene worthy men, that haue put on ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue with their Armour, and vices with their gowne, that is in exerciſe and ſorrow and acuerſity, in diſtreſſe, in action and armes haue beene very vigilant and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant; but comming to peace and eaſe and lulled in pleaſures lap, haue falne a ſleepe if not ſwounded, yea they haue grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falne, if not falne quite away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> yet is more particular, and heere
<pb facs="tcp:13106:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>may ſtand for any faithfull ſoule, which ſhall haue her time of trouble, that is of aduerſitie and tentation: therefore hee muſt looke firſt he bee a <hi>Iacob,</hi> that is an innocent and harmeleſſe man, and then to looke for his oppreſsion and trouble;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Syrac.</hi> 2.1.</note> for as <hi>Syracides</hi> ſaid, My ſonne haſt thou entred into the feate of the Lord, prepare thy ſoule to tentation? and the inſtance is notable in the perſon of Chriſt, that though hee were perſecuted by <hi>Herod</hi> while he was an infant, yet was he not tempted till after Baptiſme: to ſhew that ſo ſoone as wee giue our names to God and take vp our holy life, then comes the ſorrowe and perſecution for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and if he haue care to ſerue God and ſeuer himſelfe from the prophane faſhion of this world, hee is derided and ſcorned, as <hi>Noah</hi> was when the Arke was a making; traduced by odious and diſgracefull names, and loaden with infinite iniuries, as if he were a marke for all the Diuels ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. Yet <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt haue patience, and in all this, addreſſe himſelfe to God, not
<pb facs="tcp:13106:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhrinking in theſe aduerſities and wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, no more then that holy Patriarch did,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.31.</note> who ouercame and preuailed with the Angel, though he went away halting; we ſhall haue from the world a touch of ſorrow to carry to our graues, but there it ſhould be buried, and that which ſhal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is comfort euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>And now as this day and time admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth in this <hi>Iacobs</hi> trouble, I find a more excellent perſon, to which it is applied, that is to our verie <hi>Nathanaell i.</hi> the gift of God, his ſacred Maieſtie, who may take vp Iſraels complaint in a ſong of degrees, for the degrees of his ſorrowe, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from his youth vp, he was afflicted may Iſrael now ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 129.1.</note> &amp; the plowers plowed on his back, &amp; made long furrows, that in a great &amp; noble kingdome, from a yere old to this day, is by God vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from dangers, thogh not freed from troubles; for cares infinite are wrapped vp in the crownes of princes, &amp; they are more noble then happy, &amp; many troubles atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon their perſons, becauſe as in <hi>Eſay</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:13106:38"/>key of gouernement hangs vpon their ſhoulder: and like the Maſter-pilot guids the ſhippe of the Common-wealth, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the ſterne in euery ſtorme; ſo that the troubles of a carefull Prince are more then the labours of any common ſubiect; and the dangers of the head, more then of all the bodie. Let vs then that are but legges and hands or other parts, labour to ſupport this <hi>Iacob,</hi> not trouble <hi>Iacob,</hi> but as much as we may free him from troubles; I meane from griefe and ſorrowes; for it cannot be but the head wil ake if the body be diſtempered: and the good and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full head will watch, and heare, and ſee, and ſearch, and find out, and remedie all that may offend, and hurt the bodie, or els the head is not a head of care, but a drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie and a ſleepie part; which if it doe but ſlumber, troubles are then ſent both to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake the Pilot &amp; the Marriners; for in the head you ſee the members are vnited, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> for <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that is the whole people; <hi>Iacob</hi> for euery faithfull man, <hi>Iacob</hi> for the Prince of <hi>Iacob;</hi> in euery of theſe is ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:13106:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>a day of trouble. <hi>Sed tamen,</hi> But yet; that is, I the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> in deſpite of them al, I will deliuer him. And this ſhewes Gods owne oppoſing himſelfe againſt all the troubles and troublers of <hi>Iacob.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I wil inſtance in two moſt famous par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and ſet before your eyes the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God to this kingdome, in the daies of our late moſt noble Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> worthy of al our memories, vnder whom you haue beene bred, nurſed and brought vp: and the happie and moſt ioyfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of our ſo Noble a king, vnder whom we are ſtill ſo godly, ſo louingly and ſo peaceably gouerned: That this day we may remember with all poſsible thankes to God, both their miraculous preſeruations with a <hi>Sed tamen,</hi> that is, in deſpite of all their enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the glorie of her Sex while ſhe liued, and the honour of it beeing dead; a name ſignifying the oath of God, as if God had ſworne to be mercifull to England in the daies of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Many and great were her troubles, and yet deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:13106:39"/>out of all. Let goe the famous acts ſhee did; her ſuccour of afflicted ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, reliefe of diſtreſſed ſtates, power to ſettle with peace, and to ſuppreſſe by force, honour at home and fame abroad; I ſay, let theſe paſſe. But her deliuerance from Conſpitacies and bloody Treaſons, ſo many and ſo wonderfull, are to vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Demonſtrations of Gods mercie; that the goſpell of Chriſt which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, was at the firſt miraculouſly planted and eſtabliſhed, and euer ſince hath beene moſt miraculouſly preſerued and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued. Notwithſtanding all Romiſh op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which ſo frequent and deſperate plainely ſhew, that our Church hath by them beene perſecuted, the Goſpell inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſuppreſſed, the glorie of our State purpoſed to be ſupplanted, the life and honour of ſo noble a Queene ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly purſued: and yet I ſay, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all that euer they could doe, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of all Traytors (not worthy to bee named) ſhe was with her peoples peace, her State and honour, to the end of her life
<pb facs="tcp:13106:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>miraculouſly preſerued, and the Goſpell liues; and being dead, ſhee liues in their hearts that loue the goſpell.</p>
            <p>But now to ſee GODS goodneſſe ſtill, in preparing to this kingdome a king of whom I would ſay much, but that as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaid, <hi>vereor ne damnum illius laudibus me a faceret verecundia,</hi> and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch a king for ſuch a kingdome, A king of Iuſtice, a king of peace, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing was with ſuch ioy and generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, as I thinke, neuer happened in any nation: whoſe care of the afflicted and oppreſſed Iſraell, which by many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies hath ſo clearely appeared, ſhall pleade with God, and he ſhal remember it in the euill day, and when his ſoule is troubled, the Lord ſhall ſtand by him, and ſaue him aliue; and the backes and ſides of the poore relieued ſhall bleſſe him, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, cryes, and teares of his people ſhall praye for him, and they ſhall ſay; Deliuer <hi>Iacob</hi> Lorde out of all his troubles.</p>
            <p>And hath not GOD deliuered him
<pb facs="tcp:13106:40"/>in this fift day of Auguſt, as you haue heard before, and ſince his Maieſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this kingdome from other foule and trayterous attempts.</p>
            <p>But aboue all, from that ſame Salt-<hi>Peter</hi> Treaſon, or <hi>Peters</hi> ſalt Treaſon of Rome. I know Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle neuer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned his meate nor manners with this kind of ſalt: I ſay a Treaſon without all reaſon, a treaſon <hi>ſine nomine</hi> without a name, as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> notes of the face of the fourth Monarch, the firſt a Lion, the ſecond a Beare, the third a Leopard, the fourth <hi>terribilis valde,</hi> but <hi>ſine nomine, quia crudelitas eius erat ſine modo;</hi> ſuch was this, a Treaſon which neuer any age may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get: and I thinke ſo horrible as ſcarce po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity can beleeue, that euer any vipers bred in any Countrey, would ſo bloudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betray their ſoueraigne Lord, him and his, All the Orders and States of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and kingdome and all: ſuch a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo conceiued, conſpired, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſo concealed to a point of time, and then ſo mercifully diſcouered, tell me
<pb facs="tcp:13106:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>what God is there to the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and who ſo great, yea adde this, and who ſo good a God as Englands God? let Rome if ſhe pleaſe, boaſt of her miracles, and her raſh, and <hi>Garnets</hi> ſtrawe, all not worth a ſtraw, we will reioyce in the name of our God, and make our boaſt of him, that hath deliuered vs from ſo great a death and will deliuer; hath planted the goſpell, and no power can ſupplant it; hath peſeru'd our ſtate, and ſtil preſerues it; hath confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his mercie to vs, by his word conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued it, in the hopefull ſucceſsion of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hath ſaued our king out of the hands of all his enemies, and will ſaue him from the euill day, from the ſorrowfull Alas, from the great dayes of trouble, from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and priuy enemies, from al that beare euill will at <hi>Jacob:</hi> and the Lord is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and hath promiſed <hi>(Sed tamen)</hi> that is, let them doe what they can, in deſpite of them all, he is yet, and yet he ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered. Which ſince our eyes haue ſeene, and our eares haue now heard the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord vnto our king, and vs in
<pb facs="tcp:13106:41"/>this his day of mercie: Let vs euer pray that God would continue them ſtill; and let our hearts ioyfully giue thankes, and for theſe bleſsings euer aſcribe to God our heauenly father, to Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, our bleſſed Lord and only Sauiour, and to the holy ſpirit our true and eternall Comforter, three perſons and one God, All glorie, honour, praiſe and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, this day and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13106:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
